After discussing Access Control Lists and
Capabilities, we can now move to a different
topic, that of Authentication.
Simply put, authentication is needed to be
sure (to the extent possible) about who the
user is before enforcing a certain policy.
This is because, as we saw, policies are user-specific.
There are different ways for a user to prove
he/she is who he/she says: one option can
be for the user to show that he/she knows
something (like a password),
another to prove that he/she has something,
or to prove that he/she is someone.
These methods can of course be used not only
in isolation but also combined.
If we focus on passwords, which are the solution
that is commonly adopted, we can agree on
the fact that the following are all bad ideas
(you can have a look at this by yourself).
A prominent example of why these are all bad
ideas is the Stuxnet attack; you can search
for it and will see how something critical
has the Iranian nuclear program has been affected
by one of these bad ideas.
Once agreed that storing directly the password
associated with each user is not a good idea,
we can look at how authentication works in
Unix.
A simple form of authentication (which is
not adopted because it is not secure enough)
is to store the result obtained when encrypting
a fixed block of data with the user password
rather than storing the password itself.
As we mentioned before, if we have a cryptographically
secure one-way function f it means that from
x we can compute y = f(x) but from y it is
infeasible to find out x (which would be the
password in this case).
Notice that, in this case, it is nonetheless
possible to exploit dictionary attacks (simply
put, to try all common passwords/combinations
of words until one matches the encrypted set
of characters).
Notice that if a match is found, all users
having the same encryption result also have
the same password.
A variation to make Unix authentication more
secure is that of using an additional n-bit
salt (a random prefix of n bits) for each
user password.
Assuming that the value is indeed random and
cannot be found out by the attacker, this
implies that each word in the dictionary should
be tested with 2^n prefixes, which for large-enough
n values becomes infeasible
A different alternative is to use one-time
passwords. In this case, an interesting example
is that of one-way hash chain functions.
Supposing you have at your disposition a cryptographically
secure one-way function (here simply called
a hash function) for which the input and the
output have the same length, and also supposing
you want to use up to n one-time passwords,
you can compute the first password (P1) applying
the function n times, as shown in the slide.
P2 can be computed applying the function n–1
times and, in general, the i-th password can
be computed applying the function over the
(i+1)-th function.
That is, if you want to check that password
i+1 is correct, you can check that its hash
equals password i (but remember you cannot
find password i+1 from password i).
In this case, the server can store P0 and
value 1.
When the user wants to connect, the server
requests password 1, and to check if it is
correct, it hashes it and compares it with
the local one.
If they are the same, then the server can
increase its value to 2 (it means next time
it will ask the user to give password 2) and
update its local password value to P1.
And this, of course, can be repeated up to
n times.
As I mentioned before, there are several ways
in which authentication can be performed.
An alternative to passwords is that of challenge-response
authentication.
A simple way to implement this is to choose
as the secret to share the answer to a certain
question, an answer that is known by the user
but not by anyone else. This of course still
requires the server-side storing to be secure!
The user might also choose a certain algorithm
and provide the output of such algorithm to
the input provided by the server (in this
case the algorithm cannot be trivial, otherwise
the attacker can learn it easily).
Finally, a way to go is also for the server
and user to share an initial password k and
for both to compute a certain function f over
k and a value r shared by the server. If f
is a complex function (and user/server have
enough computational power to run it) and
both k and r are large enough, it might be
infeasible for the attacker to recover k (even
if f is known).
Other alternatives include authentication
using physical objects such as smart cards
and biometrics.
In the case of biometrics, an important aspect
to account for is variability, to have enough
distance in the features between users while
allowing some distance even for the same user
(our face does not look always the same, to
make a simple example).
Of course, another important aspect is to
realize many techniques can be used at the
same time.
If we focus on cards, we can distinguish at
least three types.
Magnetic stripe cards that contain read-only
values (the password for instance),
chip cards that contain values that can be
updated, and
Smart cards that also mount a small CPU and
are also capable of participating in the check
for authentication, for instance when using
challenge-response authentication,
or by having the cards computing a small encrypted
message (that could be helpful when buying
something and having no connectivity) and
then giving such token to the seller, who
can give it later on to the bank to claim
the money